All right. בוקר טוב, Boker tov, we're in
מסכת זבחים Masechet Zvachim דף י״ג Daf Yud Gimmel at the top
of the עמוד amud of עמוד א׳, Amud Aleph, six line from
the top we're beginning with the משנה Mishna at the top of
the page. משנה. Mishna. הפסח והחטאת ששחטן שלא לשמן קיבל והלך וזרק
שלא לשמן או לשמן ושלא לשמן או שלא לשמן ולשמן פסולים. HaPesach
ve'hachatat she'shachatan she'lo lishmon, kibel ve'halach ve'zarak she'lo lishmon, o lishmon u'she'lo
lishmon, o she'lo lishmon u'lishmon, pesulim. What did it just say? Okay,
the Pesach offering and this is like a poem, right? It's like
doesn't matter what else came after, right? If it starts out bad
it's so so if there is an element that's not focused, right?
That's not לשמה, lishmah, whether it is in each one of the
four עבודות avodot or it is in just some of them. So
in the beginning it was לא לשמה lo lishmah and then it
became לשמה lishmah or in the beginning it was לשמה lishmah and
then it becomes לא לשמה. lo lishmah. However however the order is,
it is פסול. pasul. There has to be intent in each one
of the עבודות. avodot. Do you remember what the עבודות avodot are?
Put them up because we're going to need them. שחיטה, shechitah, קבלה,
kabbalah, הולכה, holachah, and זריקה. zrikah.
Okay,
we slaughter the animal, we drain the blood, we walk the stuff
to the altar to where we're going to sacrifice and we sprinkle
the blood. That is going to be critical for the next as
many minutes as we have. All right. כיצד לשמן ושלא לשמן, Keitzad
lishmon ve'she'lo lishmon,
so what is the situation that we can do something for its
sake and not for its sake? לשם פסח ולשם שלמים. Leshem Pesach
u'leshem shelamim.
So possibly this would be somebody who's preparing a Pesach offering and
then changes the intent of it, changes his mind and makes it
for
שלמים shelamim or שלא לשמן ולשמן. she'lo lishmon ve'lishmon. He starts for
שלמים shelamim and then he's like oh actually it's Pesach let me
make this a Pesach offering.
Can't can't redirect. שהזבח נפסל בארבעה דברים, She'hazevach nifsal be'arba'ah devarim, בשחיטה
ובקיבול ובהילוך ובזריקה. be'shechitah u've'kibbul u've'hiluch u've'zrikah.
So how can a sacrifice be disqualified, be פסול pasul through something
getting in the way of one of these four things: the שחיטה,
shechitah, the slaughter; קבלה, kabbalah, accepting the blood; the הולכה, holachah, walking
it; and the זריקה. zrikah. רבי שמעון מכשיר בהילוך. Rabbi Shimon machshir
be'hiluch. Rabbi Shimon says that actually the
הילוך, hiluch, when we're walking it, if we had an unintentional thought
that would be okay. שהיה אומר, She'hayah omer, why is he why
is he coming up with this idea? אי אפשר שלא בשחיטה ושלא
בקבלה ושלא בזריקה אבל אפשר בלא הילוך. Iy efshar she'lo be'shechitah, ve'she'lo
be'kabbalah, ve'she'lo be'zrikah, aval efshar be'lo hiluch.
So what is he saying?
If I have an animal that I want to bring as a
sacrifice, some of these עבודות avodot are inevitable. I have to do
them in order to have a sacrifice. I have to slaughter.
Can't have a sacrifice without
a slaughter. It's hard to have a sacrifice without a slaughter. It's
also hard to have a sacrifice if I didn't let the blood,
right, run out. It's also hard to have a sacrifice if I
didn't sprinkle it in the appropriate place because we'll see the sprinkling,
we'll see in just a minute, is really the the ריצוי, ritzui,
the acceptance of the sacrifice. But הולכה, holachah, maybe I don't have
to walk it. How what kind of situation can I imagine that
I don't have to walk it? Without peeking, any ideas? Well, it
says it right here. I know, but we could be saying it
may be the English I peeked. No peeking. You put it on
a wagon?
No, putting it on a wagon is still הליכה, halichah, still הולכה,
holachah, walking it. The גמרא Gemara tells, the משנה Mishna tells us,
שוחט בצד המזבח וזורק. Shochet be'tzad ha'mizbeach ve'zorek. So instead of slaughtering
in point A and then walking it to the מזבח, mizbeach, I
can slaughter right there by the מזבח mizbeach and sprinkle and then
I don't need to walk it. Okay, we will unpack all of
this in length in the גמרא, Gemara, so wait. Okay, still in
the משנה. Mishna. רבי אליעזר אומר המהלך במקום שצריך להלך מחשבה פוסלת
במקום שאינו צריך להלך אין מחשבה פוסלת. Rabbi Eliezer omer ha'mehalech be'makom
she'tzarich le'halech machshavah poselet, be'makom she'eino tzarich le'halech ein machshavah poselet. So
if someone... body is walking with the sacrifice where he's supposed to
be for the sake of fulfilling the sacrifice and he has a
intervening thought then this could disqualify the
sacrifice. But if for some reason he's walking somewhere else, I don't
know wherever, he forgot his wallet at the entrance to the היכל.
Heichal. No, I don't really have a situation, but if he's walking
where he's not supposed to be and he has a thought that's
not related to the קרבן, Korban, it is not פוסל. posel. All
right, jumping into the גמרא. Gemara. Maybe it means, I don't know
if he has to be on the north side and he's coming
around in a different direction than a normal way. Like he's walking
where he's not supposed to. Or yeah, maybe or whatever. Is this
any unrelated thought or is this just the לא לשמה? lo lishma?
There is going to be a lot of discussion about what kind
of thought is in and what kind of thought is out. What
we started with is only the לשמה lishma and the לא לשמה
lo lishma which means I intended to bring a שלמים shlamim and
all of a sudden I'm like, oh gee, yesterday I also made
a great sin, let me change what this קרבן Korban is all
about. So that would be the לשמה lishma and the לא לשמה.
lo lishma. But now we're going to be in, and I don't
know if introduced, we're going to come across מחשבת פיגול. machshavat pigul.
Okay, we discussed it a few days ago. Okay, so we're going
to come across the פיגול pigul and we're going to have to
distinguish between what is a מחשבת פיגול machshavat pigul and what is
a מחשבה שלא לשמה machshava shelo lishma when
which is disqualifying a קרבן. Korban. Get ready for roller coaster. All
right, גמרא Gemara is asking: וקבלה מי פסלה? vekabala mi pasla? So
there is a tradition,
we know of something that the collection of blood according to some
it can disqualify the offer. So we're going to talk again about
the four עבודות avodot and see how to unpack those and what
is each one doing.
והתניא veha tanya first ברייתא. braita. We have a פסוק pasuk in
ויקרא Vayikra and if you have a תנ"ך Tanakh to have the
or in a book the four פסוק, pasuk, פסוק pasuk will help.
The פסוק pasuk says:
ושחט, veshachat, I'm giving us the whole פסוק pasuk even though the
גמרא Gemara is only dealing with one word from it והקריבו. vehikrivu.
Okay. ושחט את בן הבקר לפני ה' והקריבו בני אהרן הכהנים
את הדם וזרקו את הדם על המזבח סביב אשר פתח אהל מועד.
veshachat et ben habakar lifnei Hashem vehikrivu bnei Aharon hakohanim et hadam
vezarku et hadam al hamizbeach saviv asher petach Ohel Moed.
Without making this a quiz, there is three verbs in this פסוק:
pasuk: ושחט veshachat slaughtered, והקריבו vehikrivu and they something I will not
translate for a minute, וזרקו vezarku and they sprinkled the blood. Okay.
The גמרא Gemara is telling us in this section והקריבו זו קבלת
הדם. vehikrivu zu kabalat hadam. This word והקריבו vehikrivu often translated as
sacrifice, this is the קבלה kabala of the דם. dam. This is
receiving the blood. Okay, so this is right here.
So stupid, whatever, I can do more of a שיעור shiur of
a back and forth for the time, but time won't take too
much. The three verbs in the פסוק: pasuk:
שחיטה, shechita, הקרבה hakrava and זריקה. zerika. Two of them we have
in the list of the four עבודות: avodot: שחיטה shechita and זריקה.
zerika. But what about the middle? The גמרא Gemara tells us that
והקריבו vehikrivu is קבלת הדם. kabalat hadam. And now the גמרא Gemara
is going to ask about it and we can talk about it
for a minute. אתה אומר קבלת הדם או אינו אלא זריקה? ata
omer kabalat hadam o eino ela zerika? How do I know? How
do I know that והקריבו vehikrivu is דווקא davka קבלת הדם? kabalat
hadam? And the גמרא Gemara says: כשהוא אומר וזרקו הרי זריקה. kshehu
omer vezarku harei zerika.
אמור מה אני מקיים והקריבו? emor ma ani mikayem vehikrivu? זו קבלת
הדם. zu kabalat hadam.
Fantastic רש"י Rashi on it, which I am super excited about.
Doesn't happen often in this מסכת. masechet. Okay, so we have a,
I'll give you and I did not, well, there is רש"י Rashi
but then I didn't see the rest of what I'm thinking somewhere
else, so if it's stay theoretical. We have the שחיטה shechita in
the פסוק pasuk and we have the זריקה. zerika. The גמרא Gemara
says it's קבלה kabala והקריבו. vehikrivu. What is the meaning of והקריבו?
vehikrivu? Literally we translate it as sacrifice, not slaughter, sacrifice right? קרבן
Korban is a sacrifice. But what is the שורש shoresh of והקריבו?
vehikrivu?
To come near? To come near. So this is how we come
near. So רש״י Rashi says why קבלה kabala and not הולכה? holacha?
How do I know which one of the מלאכות melachot it is?
It could be either one. To summarize the רש״י Rashi there if
you want to look at it later, it says הולכה holacha is
a language of coming near and also קבלה kabala is לשון lashon
of coming near. It's like something that I do to come close.
What is so fantastic for me? Don't shoot me. קבלה, kabala, we
know what קבלה kabala is, right? We also know הולכה. holacha. We
have a word הלכה. halacha. And just coincidentally, because I like Hebrew,
so these are like two ways of coming near to השם Hashem
to be קרוב. karov. קרוב karov also.
קרב krav battle you mean?
Coming near in a hostile sense. Could could be also what do
we mean by sacrifice, right? Okay. So I I'm gonna take it
only as much time and where I can take it right now.
But these to me indicate two ways that we can come close.
One is passive and one is active. One just happens. The קבלה
kabala just happens. The blood just pours out of the animal. Once
I slaughter it, I don't have to do anything. The הולכה holacha
is active. Also in our life, in our relationship with השם Hashem
maybe slightly דרש-יק, drashic, we have a קבלה kabala and הולכה holacha
and רש״י Rashi says they're really part of the same thing. We
have a מסורה masora that סברא sevara that מה שנוהג בקבלה נוהג
בהולכה. ma she'noheg b'kabala noheg b'holacha. It's the same, they're like connected.
Okay, continuing back to the פסוק, pasuk, to the whole פסוק, pasuk,
it says בני אהרן הכהנים. Bnei Aharon ha'Kohanim. So one is the
והקריבו ve'hikrivu is by קבלה. kabala. בני אהרן הכהנים Bnei Aharon ha'Kohanim
it says in the פסוק. pasuk. What does that mean? שתהא בכהן
כשר ובכלי שרת. she'tehei b'kohen kasher u'v'kli sharet. So the כהן kohen
has to be a כהן כשר, kohen kasher, not חלל, chalal, not
בעל מום, ba'al mum, and כלי שרת kli sharet means they have
to be dressed in their כהונה, kehuna, in their priestly vestments. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is going to challenge our ברייתא. beraita.
אמר רבי עקיבא, amar Rabbi Akiva, מנין לקבלה שלא תהא אלא בכהן
כשר ובכלי שרת? minayin l'kabala she'lo tehei ela b'kohen kasher u'v'kli sharet?
Where do I know this from? So luckily we have a whole
מסכת masechet in front of us and it's going to come in
some future pages. Here we have just one פסוק. pasuk. It doesn't
explain it perfectly but it gives us some hint. He contrasts it
with a verse from במדבר Bamidbar in the beginning of במדבר Bamidbar
and I
have the verse. Where is my verse? 3-3 maybe? In beginning of
במדבר, Bamidbar, אלה שמות בני אהרן הכהנים המשוחים אשר מלא ידם לכהן.
eleh shemot b'nei Aharon ha'kohanim ha'meshuchim asher milei yadam l'khahen. We're asking
what is מלא ידם לכהן? milei yadam l'khahen? This is their their
garments.
And since there in במדבר Bamidbar we're talking about a כהן כשר
kohen kasher and a כלי שרת, kli sharet, here also we're talking
about a כהן כשר וכלי שרת. kohen kasher v'kli sharet. It's not
exactly obvious. But I guess we know that at the time we're
talking about איתמר Itamar and אלעזר Elazar the sons of אהרן, Aaron,
that they were כשרים ksherim and they were serving in their in
their vestments. Okay.
There's a note here. Yes. Just going back just a little bit
where it's an earlier reference in שמות Shemot that's saying suggesting that.
In תצוה Tetzaveh in the garments of the כהונה. kehuna. No, not
the garments. No, but it's suggesting that because משה Moshe received the
blood in a vessel, that's the רש״י. Rashi. Right. Yes. That's the
רש״י Rashi that since משה Moshe received the blood in a vessel
we understand that there's a vessel. Right. But how do we know
that קבלה kabala and הולכה holacha are both in the והקריבו? ve'hikrivu?
That's
my understanding is that that's a like it's a סברא. sevara. That's
kind of something that רש״י Rashi comes to teach us that those
two things have to do with the קרבן. korban.
Fantastic exchange here between רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon and רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. אמר רבי
טרפון, amar Rabbi Tarfon, אקפח את בני אם לא שמעתי להבחין הפרש
בין קבלה לזריקה ואין לי לפרש. akapeach et banai im lo shamati
l'havchin hefresh bein kabala l'zerika v'ein li l'faresh. רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon
says in a
he like cries out the pain of תורה. Torah. If you think
רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon is older than רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, so
we know they're both living through the destruction of the temple, right?
And this like loss that we have. And now he's like totally
distressed, he forgot a piece of תורה. Torah. He says, by my
life, it's like I I'm willing to give up my kids, right,
if my sons, if I haven't heard some distinction between קבלה kabala
and זריקה zerika and ways that they're not the same. Right now
they're for us ארבע עבודות arba avodot that we're doing with the
sacrifice. I remember some distinction but I don't remember what it is.
We learn it as if they're four of them are the same.
רבי טרפון Rabi Tarfon says to us, I remember some distinctions, I
have no idea anymore what it is. רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva the
younger, slightly חוצפהדיק chutzpadik rabbi says, מה רבי עקיבא אני אפרש. Mah
Rabi Akiva Ani Afareish. I did not study with you רבי טרפון
Rabi Tarfon but I have no problem of bringing the דרשה drasha
on us. And he brings three things. We'll read the three and
then go over them.
קבלה לא עשה בה מחשבה כמעשה. Kabala lo asah bah machshava kemaseh.
זריקה עשה בה מחשבה כמעשה. Zerika asah bah machshava kemaseh. That's the
first distinction. Two: קיבלו בחוץ אינו חייב כרת. Kiblo bachutz eino chayav
kares. זרקו בחוץ ענוש כרת. Zerako bachutz anush kares.
Three: קיבלוהו פסולין אין חייבין עליו. Kiblohu psulin ein chayavim alav. זרקוהו
פסולין חייבין עליו. Zerakoho psulin chayavim alav. What is he saying? He
says in קבלה, kabala, if there is a wrong thought—we will
discuss in length what exactly do we mean by a wrong thought—but
he says לא עשה בה מחשבה כמעשה. lo asah bah machshava kemaseh.
Like the thought and the action don't mean the same thing, i.e.,
the action must be right, right? So if the thought is not
right, that's okay in קבלה. kabala. But in זריקה, zerika, the intent
and the act must be together. Two: If you do the קבלה
kabala outside, then there's no כרת, kares, but if you do the
sprinkling outside of the designated areas for the קרבנות, korbanot, then the
person will be liable for כרת. kares. And the third one: קיבלוהו
פסולין אין חייבין עליו. Kiblohu psulin ein chayavim alav. If somebody who
is פסול pasul received
the blood, was there at the קבלה kabala of the blood, there's
no
חייבין דין מיתה, chayavim din mita, you're not liable to a death
penalty. But if sprinkling is done by somebody who is not—who is
פסול, pasul, then there is חובה. chova. Okay. אמר לו רבי טרפון—you
Amar lo Rabi Tarfon gotta love this exchange here—אמר לו רבי טרפון
העבודה, Amar lo Rabi Tarfon ha-avoda, like this is a language of
an oath. Wow, I swear by the temple, right, by the service
in the temple. את הטית ימין ושמאל אני שמעתי ואין לי לפרש
ואתה דורש ומסכים לשמועה. At hitit yamin usmoal ani shamati ve'ein li
lefareish ve'atah doreish umas'kim lashmu'ah. I,
he says, wow, you have not made a difference left or right,
you said it right on. I heard and I can't make a
commentary. You just דורש doreish and say the right thing. בלשון הזה
אמר לו עקיבא כל הפורש ממך
כפורש מחייו. Balashon hazeh amar lo Akiva kol haporeish mimcha keporeish mechayav.
Anyone who leaves you is like leaving his life. In another לשון,
lashon, look at the repeating of this שורש shoresh פרש. parash. Right?
First when רבי טרפון Rabi Tarfon says it, אם לא שמעתי להבחין
הפרש לפרש. im lo shamati lehavchin hefreish lefareish. Right? I didn't hear
a difference between קבלה kabala and זריקה zerika and I don't have
לפרש lefareish to commentary. רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva says אני אפרש. Ani
afareish. And at the end he says to him, עקיבא כל הפורש
ממך, Akiva kol haporeish mimcha, anyone who deviates from you is as
if he deviates from life. Really like
wow wow wow.
But now we still have a problem. We have a wow, but
we have a problem because we said in the very beginning of
this מסכת masechet that these four עבודות avodot must be לשמה. lishma.
And רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva now says to us about קבלה kabala
that it can have a not right thought
and this would be okay.
Repeat? You were good.
We were talking about the לשמה lishma and we said they all
have to be לשמה. lishma. We have to have an intent in
the sacrifice that this is what the sacrifice is for. And all
of a sudden רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva here—I'm already putting a different
column—he brings—he says that it's okay in קבלה kabala to have a
different thought. These three still have to be intent, but in קבלה
kabala it's okay. So we have a problem between our משנה mishna
and the ברייתא braita of רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva and רבי טרפון.
Rabi Tarfon. אמר רבא, לא קשיא. Amar Rava lo kashya. Why do
you guys think it's a problem? There is no problem at all.
The תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, the contradiction's with the תנא קמא, Tanna
Kamma, not רבי טרפון, Rabi Tarfon, right? We have the discussion of
רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva and רבי טרפון Rabi Tarfon in the ברייתא,
braita, as opposed to the משנה, mishna, yes, as opposed to the
תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. אמר רבא Amar Rava, לא קשיא. lo kashya.
Why do you guys think it's a problem? There's no problem at
all. כאן במחשבת פיגול, Kan Bemachshevet Pigul, כאן במחשבת שלא לשמה. Kan
Bemachshevet Shelo Lishma.
So we are looking at a different kind of
inappropriate thinking for the sacrifice in context of the sacrifices, which is
the פיגול. Pigul.
What is פיגול? Pigul? Everyone knows
it has to do with the right time. פיגול Pigul has to
do with right time and מחשבה שלא לשמה Machshava Shelo Lishma means
I intend to bring this sacrifice for the sake of another sacrifice.
Okay.
So Rava says this is going to be the distinction and we're
going to keep, we're going to come back to it and continue,
continue discussing the פיגול. Pigul. Okay.
דיקא נמי דקתני שהזבח נפסל ולא קטני מתפגל. Deika Nami Dekatani Shehazevach
Nifsal Velo Katani Mitpagel. Indeed, the Gemara adds, notice the precise language
of the Mishnah. The Mishnah talks to us about the זבח, Zevach,
the offering, being פסול, Pasul, being disqualified, and it didn't tell us
that the offering might be מתפגל, Mitpagel, right, might be having a
פיגול Pigul in it. So שמע מינה, Shema Mina, indeed that is
the difference. But we're continuing, not so simple.
Okay. ומחשבת פיגול לא פסלה בקבלה? Umachshevet Pigul Lo Pesala Bekabala? Really?
Like, the פיגול, Pigul, the thought of the kind of wrong thing,
it's not—doesn't that disqualify the קבלה? Kabala? Because right now we're saying
לשמה Lishma everything, פיגול Pigul here, maybe, maybe it's okay to have
it. It's okay to have a wrong thought. All right. So now
we're going to look at another ברייתא. Beraita.
Okay.
Our ברייתא Beraita brings us a פסוק Pasuk that we're going to
need for, again, throughout this, this דף. Daf. It's from ויקרא
Vayikra 7:18. And
okay, let me read us the ברייתא Beraita and then the, bring
the פסוק Pasuk and its fullness so we can understand what's, hopefully,
what's going on.
דהתניא, De-Tanya, יכול לא תהא מחשבה מועלת אלא בזריקה בלבד. Yachol Lo
Tehe Machshava Moelet Ela Bezrika Bilvad. מנין לרבות שחיטה וקבלה? Minayin Lerabot
Shechita Vekabala? How do I know that in זריקה, Zrika, שחיטה, Shechita,
and קבלה, Kabala, I need to have appropriate thoughts not just in
the לשמה Lishma but also in the פיגול, Pigul, also in, in
the time of the קרבן? Korban? And here is my פסוק. Pasuk.
In Leviticus 7:18 it says, ואם האכל יאכל מבשר זבח
שלמיו ביום השלישי לא ירצה המקריב אתו לא יחשב לו פגול יהיה
והנפש האכלת ממנו עונה תשא. Ve-im He-achol Ye-achel Mibesar Zevach Shelamav Bayom
Hashlishi Lo Yeratzel Hamakriv Oto Lo Yechashev Lo Pigul Yiheyeh Vehanefesh Ha-ochelet
Mimenu Avonah Tisa.
It would be fascinating if we didn't have to race through the
דף Daf to look at this פסוק Pasuk and think, what are
some of the things that would be red flags for the Rabbis?
So we have אם אכול האכל, Im Achol He-achol, we have a
duplication of the verb לאכול. Le-echol. בשר זבח שלמיו, Besar Zevach Shelamav,
our focus point is the שלמים. Shelamim. ביום השלישי, Bayom Hashlishi, which
is the day past the שלמים Shelamim is edible. לא ירצה Lo
Yeratzel won't be accepted. המקריב אתו לא יחשב לו, Hamakriv Oto Lo
Yechashev Lo, the one that sacrifices, it's not counting for him. פיגול
יהיה. Pigul Yiheyeh. This is our source for the thought of פיגול
Pigul and from here we understand as many things as we can.
Okay. The גמרא Gemara tells us, בדברים המביאים לידי אכילה הכתוב מדבר.
Bidevarim Hamveeyim Lidei Achila Hakatuv Medaber. The פיגול Pigul is with everything
that's related to preparing the sacrifice to be eaten. And as we'll
see, the גמרא Gemara will discuss what exactly is the definition of
preparing a sacrifice to be eaten. Is draining the blood preparing or
is slaughtering and carrying it or sprinkling it preparing, preparing the sacrifice?
Okay. The
ברייתא Beraita is continuing...
okay, we'll come back to it. The ברייתא Beraita continues, יכול שאני
מרבה אף שפיכת שיריים והקטרת אימורין. Yachol She-ani Marbe Af Shefichat Shirayim
Vehaktarat Imurin. So maybe I should include also the שפיכת שיריים, Shefichat
Shirayim, which is pouring the remainder of the blood on the base
of the מזבח Mizbeach after, after it was sprinkled and הקטרת אימורין,
Haktarat Imurin, and burning the portions, yeah, on the, on the altar.
תלמוד לומר, Talmud Lomar, ביום השלישי לא ירצה המקריב אתו לא יחשב.
Bayom Hashlishi Lo Yeratzel Hamakriv Oto Lo Yechashev. Therefore the verse that
we just read says... This, it says to us ביום השלישי לא
ירצה *bayom hashlishi lo yeiratzeh* and we learn understand this רצוי *ritzui*,
I had this word two days ago, this acceptance, that is
the time of the
זריקה zerika. *zrika*.
Maybe because that's like the finalizing of the sacrifice but that indicates
the רצוי *ritzui* indicates the acceptance of the sacrifice. Also it's the
connection with the altar.
Okay. In terms of being the accept, the altar's accepting the דם
*dam*. Right. And and giving a hopefully a כפרה kapara, *kaparah*. So
that would be important for us to keep through this that the
רצוי *ritzui* is the זריקה zerika, *zrika*, the being accepted is the
זריקה zrika *zrika*.
Okay. So זריקה zrika *zrika* was in the כלל *klal*, was with
all the עבודות avodot. *avodot*, right? Why did this פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*
take it out? Why is this, why is it specifying it, right,
as a different as a מוציא זה מן הכלל *motzi zeh min
haklal*, takes it out of the whole category? ולמה יצאה להקיש אליה
לומר לך מה זריקה zrika, מיוחדת שהיא עבודה מכפרת ומעכבת כפרה kapara,
אף כל עבודה ומעכבת כפרה kapara, יצאו שפיכת שיריים והקטרת אימורים שאין
מעכבים את הכפרה *velamah yatzah lehakish eleiha lomar lach mah zrika meyuchadet
shehi avodah mechaperet umeakevet kaparah af kol avodah umeakevet kaparah
yatzu shfichat shirayim vehaktarat eimurim she'ein me'akvim et hakaparah*. Okay. Why do
I need the sprinkling, why do I have it set aside? Because
there's something unique about sprinkling. Without it, without the זריקה zrikah. *zrika*,
the קרבן korban *korban* doesn't atone. It's as if the קרבן korban
*korban* is not complete and it doesn't atone. So it wants
to tell us that every עבודה *avodah* that is מעכב me'akev כפרה
kapara, *me'akev kaparah*, that like delays the atonement, also it teaches
us about that that it's necessary. יצאו שפיכת שיריים והקטרת אימורים *yatzu
shfichat shirayim vehaktarat eimurim*, we just read it, שאין מעכבים את הכפרה
*she'ein me'akvim et hakaparah*. So the like the latter עבודות avodot. *avodot*,
pouring the remainder of the blood and burning the sacrificial portion it
says, they are not preventing atonement. Okay. So okay,
so we still are in the question of where can
we have this מחשבת פיגול pigul *machshevet pigul*. אלא *ela*,
top of י"ג עמוד ב *yud gimmel amud bet*, אלא לא קשיא
lo kashya, *ela lo kashya*, not at all a problem. הא דאמר
ha d'amar, הריני שוחט shochet על מנת לקבל דמה מחר הא דאמר
ha d'amar, הריני מקבל דמה על מנת לשפוך שיריים למחר *ha de'amar
hareni shochet al menat lekabel damah machar ha de'amar hareni mekabel damah
al menat lishpoch shirayim lemachar*. Okay. So there's two different options, two
different thoughts. The first, הריני שוחט על מנת לקבל דמה מחר *hareni
shochet al menat lekabel damah machar*, if I have a מחשבה מפגלת
*machshavah mefagelet* in the time of the שחיטה shechitah *shchitah*, not a
problem. If I think okay, I'm going to do this שחיטה *shchitah*
so I can have the blood tomorrow, right, we said that the
פיגול pigul. *pigul* has to do with time, that's not a פיגול
pigul. *pigul*. But if he says הריני מקבל דמה על מנת לשפוך
שיריים למחר *hareni mekabel damah al menat lishpoch shirayim lemachar*, I have
the קבלה kabbalah *kabalah* in order to pour the remainders of the
blood on the מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach* tomorrow, that's that is considered מחשבה
מפגלת *machshavah mefagelet*.
And we saw from the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* earlier everything that has
to do with אכילה achila, *achilah* can cause this פיגול pigul. *pigul*.
And since pouring the remainders, doing this שפיכת שיריים *shfichat shirayim* is
considered part of the eating on the altar, part of the אכילה
*achilah*, we'll see what exactly they're talking about, then it renders it
a פיגול pigul. *pigul*. Okay. אמר Amar, לו ההוא מרבנן לרבא ושפיכת
שיריים והקטרת אימורים לא פסלה בהו מחשבה *amar lo hahu merabanan lerava
veshfichat shirayim vehaktarat eimurim lo paslah behu machshavah*. Wait, so somebody is
asking, one of the sages is asking Rava: Does
like the wrong intent with regard to the שפיכת שיריים והקטרת אימורים
*shfichat shirayim vehaktarat eimurim*, the pouring of the remainders and burning of
the sacrificial portion, does not disqualify the offering? This is what this
explanation would indicate, right? The four עבודות avodot *avodot* and those two
extra, not. והתנן יכול לא תהא מחשבה מועלת אלא באכילת בשר *vehatnan
yakhol lo tehe machshavah mo'elet ela be'achilat basar*. מנין לרבות שפיכת שריים
shefichat she'arayim, והקטרת אימורים? How do we know that also it includes
the pouring of the remainders and the burning, the הקטרת אימורים? haktarat
imurim? ויקרא Vayikra back to this פסוק, pasuk this פסוק pasuk that
we just read is critical in order to understand everything that's that
has to do with the פיגול pigul, and one of the things
pointed out earlier that is important in this פסוק pasuk. is that
it has the verb אכל achal twice. It's האכל יאכל, he'achol ye'achel,
indeed shall be eaten. And the גמרא Gemara is asking why why
do we need it twice? בשתי אכילות הכתוב מדבר. bishtei achilot hakatuv
medaber. We're talking about two two types of אכילה, two types of
food consumption. One is by men, right, אכילת אדם, achilat adam, ואחת
אכילת מזבח. v'achat achilat mizbe'ach. One is that the human is consuming,
right, the person that's bringing is consuming or the priest, and the
other one is the altar altar, yeah, the מזבח mizbe'ach as if
the מזבח is also אוכל ochel the sacrifice and so we have
two. How do we how do we understand this? לא קשיא, nothing
is a problem for anybody.
הא דאמר, הריני זורק על מנת לשפוך שריים למחר, hareini zorek al
menat lishpoch she'arayim lemachar, this is what we just mentioned.
הא דאמר, הריני שופך שריים על
מנת
להקטיר אימורים למחר. hareini shofech she'arayim al menat lehaktir imurim lemachar. The
שופך, shofech, the second one is not פוסל. posel.
Let me see.
Yeah, with this intent rendering the the sprinkling, where there is a
wrong thought in the sprinkling, then that because the זורק, zorek, the
first one, הריני זורק על מנת לשפוך שריים למחר, hareini zorek al
menat lishpoch she'arayim lemachar, in order to be זורק, zorek, that has
to have intent and the right thought at the right time to
be accepted, so a wrong thought would be פיגול. pigul. And the
other case where we say, oh, I'm pouring the remainder,
then the intent doesn't render it פיגול. pigul.
Okay, everybody
can we breathe?
There's a summary note here. Do you want me to read? Sure.
Okay. In conclusion, there are two conditions that must be met for
a sacrifice to become פיגול. pigul. One, the improper intention must take
place during one of the blood עבודות. avodot The four? Pardon me?
Yeah, the four עבודות. avodot Right, right, the four, right. And the
second is the intention must be that an act of consumption,
pouring the remaining blood during the sacrificial pouring the remaining blood, burning
the sacrificial parts, eating the meat be performed after the allotted time.
If either of these conditions are not fulfilled, the sacrifice does not
become פיגול. pigul Okay, what
again? Did that read right? It sounds like
you're eliminating the distinction that you just made.
Because okay, I will try to read say it. The שפיכת שריים,
shefichat she'arayim pouring the leftovers, right, is not necessary
for כפרה, it's not indispensable for atonement. We don't have to have
it for the כפרה, which we do have to have is זריקה.
In זריקה, a wrong thought would be פיגול, pigul, but in the
others, I think not. Okay, hold on. Okay, they're giving like a
double negative thing here, okay, just saying if okay.
Even though the שפיכת שריים and הקטרת אימורים haktarat imurim is part
of eating, and we said earlier everything connected to eating, right, is
in the same category, but it's not considered necessary for כפרה, it's
not one of the עבודות avodot that's necessary for the כפרה, pouring
the leftovers, and therefore
that's not going to be פיגול. pigul, If there is a thought
during the שפיכה, sheficha, pouring the leftovers and burning the what was
it, the sacrificial portion, is not going to be פיגול. pigul Or
eating the meat also. Huh? Or eating the meat also.
Pouring the blood, burning the sacrificial parts, or eating the meat.
Eating the meat would seem to be clear, that that that's the
given, the question is these other two, the process. Right, before then.
All right. Deep breath, new topic. אמר רבי יהודה. Amar Rabbi Yehuda.
Okay. בריה דרבי חייא. Brei de'Rabbi Chiyya. שמעתי שטבילת אצבע
מפגלת בחטאת פנימית. Shamati she'tevilat etzba mefagelet be'chatat pnimit.
We're talking about the inner sin offering, we have an outer and
we have an inner sin offering, the חטאת פנימית. chatat pnimit.
The חטאת פנימית, chatat pnimit, the blood is sprinkled on the curtain
that separates the sanctuary from the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. Dipping one's
finger, right, in the blood in order to sprinkle it, if he
does not have the intent, right,
the intent should be that this is a חטאת chatat and the
next day we're going to burn this offering on the altar, then
it will be פיגול. pigul, It will,
yeah, okay.
Keep holding the פסוק pasuk we had earlier in mind of אם
אכול יאכל Im achol ye'achel because let's see if I can bring
it back in my notes, because this is going to be critical
since we said that we learn פיגול pigul. from this one
פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק pasuk. was ואם האכל יאכל מבשר זבח שלמיו
ביום השלישי לא ירצה המקריב אתו לא יחשב לו פגול יהיה והנפש
האכלת ממנו עונה תשא. Ve'im he'achol ye'achel mibesar zevach shelamav bayom hashelishi
lo yeratze hamakriv oto lo yechashev lo pigul yiheye ve'hanefesh ha'ochelet mimeno
avonah tisa. If you have a תנ"ך, Tanakh, it's in ויקרא Vayikra
7:18.
Okay. שמעה אילפא, Shama'ah Ilfa, Ilfa heard this statement. אמרה קמי דרב
פדא, Amrah kamei de'Rav Padda, he said it in front of Rav
Padda. אמר, said Rav Padda, כלום למדנו פיגול אלא משלמים? Kelum lamadnu
pigul ela mishlamim? Haven't we like, we learn everything we know about
פיגול, pigul. we learn from שלמים, shelamim, from this פסוק. pasuk The
question is going to be what do we learn, but everything we
learn from פיגול, pigul. we learn about פיגול pigul. we learn from
this פסוק. pasuk מה שלמים אין טבילת אצבע מפגלת בהם אף חטאת
אין טבילת אצבע מפגלת בהם. Mah shelamim ein tevilat etzba mefagelet bahem,
af chatat ein tevilat etzba mefagelet bahem. We say that just as
with regards to the שלמים, shelamim, dipping one's finger in the blood
to sprinkle it on the altar doesn't make it פיגול, pigul
so we can say that the same is for חטאת. chatat. The
problem is going to be that בשלמים be'shelamim there's no requirement to
sprinkle the blood with one's finger, okay, so we're going to see
that there's a lengthy discussion if we, if this is actually comparable.
In שלמים shelamim we have a vessel and we don't have the
finger, finger thing.
Okay.
וכי הכל משלמים למדו? Ve'chi hakol mishlamim lamdu? Did we indeed learn
all the דיני פיגול dinei pigul from שלמים? shelamim? Then we have
a problem. אימא שלמים שלא לשמן אין מוציא מידי פיגול אף חטאת
שלא לשמה אין מוציא מידי פיגול. Imah shelamim she'lo lishmam ein motzi
midei pigul, af chatat she'lo lishmah ein motzi midei pigul. So, again,
luckily this will repeat in the future דפים, dapim, specifically in דף
כ"ט, Daf Kaf-Tet, דף Daf 29, there is going to be further
discussion about it, but we'll just do the initial thing right now.
Okay, so what we're saying is this. אימא שלמים שלא לשמן אין
מוציא מידי פיגול. Imah shelamim she'lo lishmam ein motzi midei pigul. So
שלמים shelamim not for its sake does not
make it impossible to be פיגול. pigul There's probably another negative we
can add in this verse, but I'm not sure of where. Okay,
so if something, okay,
if something is not לשמו, lishmo, it can be kosher, right, but
it doesn't fulfill the obligation of the person. It can be לא
לשמו lo lishmo and still have a possibility of becoming פיגול. pigul
So too, it should be אף חטאת שלא לשמה אין מוציאים מידי
פיגול. af chatat she'lo lishmah ein motzi'im midei pigul. It should be
that also a חטאת chatat that is not for its sake, it
does not preclude it from being פיגול. pigul But this is,
and
this is the הלכה, halakha, that a חטאת chatat sacrificed not for
its sake cannot become פיגול. pigul. Can we actually, can we actually
learn from this? אלא מאי מאי אית לך למימר? Ela mai mai
itlach lemeimar?
How do you explain this הלכה? halakha? Do you, can you really
derive it from this
שלמים, shelamim, from this פסוק of שלמים? shelamim? הגמרא Ha'Gemara says: מריבוייא
דקראי קאתי. Miribuya de'krai ka'ati. We have to derive it from
like having lots of פסוקים psukim or having lots of mentions about
it. Okay
and it says and it implies here too מריבויא דקרא קאתי meribuya
dekra kaati that the הלכה halacha that prohibits intent while dipping one's
finger in the blood of the inner חטאת chatat חטאת פנימית chatat
penimit can render it פיגול pigul it's derived from lots of from
multiplicity
yes of the verse. Okay we're going to and now it's
a question and if I remember where we're going to is that
in every what we learn from the שלמים shelamim about the פיגול
pigul is that
we can have פיגול pigul. in שלמים shelamim but in every קרבן
korban, it might be there it's possible to have a פיגול pigul
thought in every קרבן korban? but it might not be exactly the
same as it is in the שלמים. shelamim. And we have two
ראיות raayot and try to at least go through part of it.
Okay first one. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי amar rabi yehoshua ben
levi בעליה זו שמעתי baaliya zu shamati שתבילת אצבע מפגלת. shetvilat etzba
mefagelet. I heard in this עליה aliya attic upper story. Okay I
heard in this place that indeed the wrong intent while dipping
one's finger in the blood of the inner חטאת chatat makes it
a פיגול. pigul. תיהי בה teihei bah רבי שמעון בן לקיש. rabi
shimon ben lakish. Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish was worried, was wondering כלום
למדו פיגול אלא משלמים? klum lamdu pigul ela mishelamim?
Did we learn the הלכות halachot of פיגול pigul from anything except
the שלמים פסוק shelamim pasuk which we had earlier? מה שלמים אין
תבילת אצבע מפגלת בהם ma shelamim ein tvilat etzba mefagelet bahem אף
חטאת אין תבילת אצבע מפגלת בהם af chatat ein tvilat etzba mefagelet
bahem and we'll see this repeating. So we can say just as
with regards to the שלמים shelamim
the wrong or prohibited intent when dipping one's finger in the blood
does not make it פיגול pigul so we can say the same
about חטאת. chatat. The הלכה halacha should be that the wrong intent
while dipping one's finger in the blood does not make it פיגול.
pigul Again the problem is going to be that שלמים shelamim doesn't
have this procedure so can we actually learn from one to another?
וכי הכל משלמים למדו? vechi hakol mishelamim lamdu? גמרא gemara repeats אם
מה מה שלמים שלא לשמם אין מוציא מידי פיגול im ma ma
shelamim shelo lishmam ein motzi miydei pigul אף חטאת שלא לשמה אין
מוציא מידי פיגול. af chatat shelo lishma ein motzi miydei pigul. We
ask the same question we brought earlier. Are we learning everything from
שלמים? shelamim? Because if so just as the שלמים shelamim that is
שלא לשמו shelo lishmo does not
preclude it from being a פיגול pigul right so too it should
be that the חטאת chatat שלא לשמה shelo lishma also
does not preclude from being a פיגול. pigul רגע. rega. רבי יוסי
ברבי חנינא rabi yosi berabi chanina
says yes. הכל משלמים אין. hakol mishelamim in.
Sorry he doesn't say yes he says אין. in. הכל משלמים למדו.
hakol mishelamim lamdu. Yeah we learn everything from שלמים. shelamim. הואיל וחוץ
למקומו פוסל בשלמים hoil vechutz limkomo posel beshelamim ושלא לשמו פוסל בחטאת.
veshelo lishmo posel bechatat.
Because we learn everything from שלמים. shelamim. Since in the case of
the שלמים shelamim the חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo the intent to eat
it outside of the designated area disqualifies as a פסול psul ושלא
לשמו פוסל בחטאת veshelo lishmo posel bechatat
and in the case of the חטאת chatat sacrificing it not for
its sake disqualifies and we've talked about it here
before that דוקא davka the חטאת chatat must must be for its
sake if this is to atone for you know for a חטא.
chet. So now we can we can learn from it מה חוץ
למקומו הפוסל בשלמים מוציא מידי פיגול ma chutz limkomo haposel beshelamim motzi
miydei pigul אף שלא לשמו הפוסל בחטאת מוציאה מידי פיגול. af shelo
lishmo haposel bechatat motziah miydei pigul. רגע. rega.
Okay so we can learn that just as the חוץ למקומו הפוסל
בשלמים chutz limkomo haposel beshelamim
intent to eat it outside the designated area which would disqualify the
שלמים shelamim precluded from being rendered a פיגול so also doing the
חטאת chatat not for its sake.
Which would disqualify it otherwise, right,
preclude its being rendered a פגול. pigul. By contrast,
okay, so what they're really- what they're really saying: dipping one's finger
in the blood of the חטאת chatat with the intent to consume
it later, after the designated time—and we talked about designated time being
an indication of the פגול—it pigul doesn't render it a פגול, pigul,
a פגול pigul is this, because there's no parallel הלכה halacha in
the שלמים. shlamim. Like, we're comparing two things that can't exactly be
compared because the שלמים shlamim doesn't have this dipping of the finger.
רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya says we can prove it from another way:
מצידה תיוברא. mitzidda tivra. אמר רבי ירמיה, amar Rabbi Yirmiya, מצידה תיוברא:
mitzidda tivra: מה לחוץ למקומו הפוסל בשלמים שכן נוהג בכל הזבחים, ma
lechutz limkomo haposel bishlamim sheken noheg bechol hazvachim, תאמר בשלא לשמו שאינו
נוהג אלא בפסח וחטאת בלבד? tomar beshelo lishmo she'eino noheg ela bepesach
vechatat bilvad? רגע, rega, not yet done
with the discussion. I feel like I have to not breathe, right?
אמר רבי ירמיה, amar Rabbi Yirmiya,
this is like מצידה תיוברא, mitzidda tivra, it's like this is- this
is disjointed, it can be proved from itself, from within. מה לחוץ
למקומו הפוסל בשלמים שכן נוהג בכל הזבחים. ma lechutz limkomo haposel bishlamim
sheken noheg bechol hazvachim. This is- what is-
what is so special about this לחוץ למקומו
lechutz limkomo that פוסל בשלמים, posel bishlamim, that eating it, consuming it
outside the designated area will disqualify the שלמים? shlamim? שכן נוהג בכל
הזבחים. sheken noheg bechol hazvachim. This is- the same disqualification will apply
to all the זבחים, zvachim,
all the slaughtered offerings, right? We have to eat them in the
correct place. תאמר בשלא לשמו שאינו נוהג אלא בפסח וחטאת בלבד? tomar
beshelo lishmo she'eino noheg ela bepesach vechatat bilvad? Then
question:
would you say the same with regards to the disqualification of שלא
לשמו, shelo lishmo, of not for its sake, which applies to פסח
pesach and the חטאת, chatat, which is where, if we still remember
where we started our משנה? mishna? אלא מה אית לך למימר? ela
ma it lach lemeimar?
Rather, what do you have to say to explain this? דבר הפוסל
בהן מוציאם מידי פגול, davar haposel bahen motzi'am midei pigul, דבר המעכב
בהן מביאם לידי פגול. davar hame'akev bahen mevi'am lidei pigul. Okay, so
we can-
we can learn it like this again: דבר הפוסל בהן מוציאם מידי
פגול. davar haposel bahen motzi'am midei pigul. Something that disqualifies the שלמים,
shlamim, like an intent, for example, an intent to eat it outside
of the designated area, preclude its being rendered a פגול. pigul. Okay,
it doesn't let it be also rendered a פגול. pigul. But דבר
המעכב, davar hame'akev, something that
prevents the goal of the sacrifice, the atonement, if not performed correctly,
does render this offering a פגול pigul if we have a thought
of consuming it outside of the designated time. I want to- I
want to make it a little further if that's okay? I hear
the silence that this needs a lot of unpacking, but- but
I'm not sure if we can do it this morning, so I
apologize. Okay. הכא נמי, hacha nami, דבר הפוסל בה מוציא מידי פגול,
davar haposel bah motzi midei pigul, דבר המעכב בה מביאה לידי פגול.
davar hame'akev bah mevi'ah lidei pigul. This is- now- okay.
רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya says this is how- what is it trying
to tell you? דבר הפוסל בהן מוציאם מידי פגול. davar haposel bahen
motzi'am midei pigul. Something that disqualifies them, I think makes it impossible
for them to be rendered a פגול. pigul. But דבר המעכב, davar
hame'akev, something that
prevents the atonement, מעכב like slowing down, if not performed- huh? Impede.
Impediments. Brings an impediment on it, then it can render it a
פגול. pigul. And so the same it is for the חטאת פנימית,
chatat pnimis, this was our discussion from רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda saying,
right, that he heard that dipping the finger in the blood can
be פגול pigul in the inner חטאת. chatat. There's a real difference
between פסל pasal and פיגל. pigel. Okay, I'm-
I'm not expert on קרבנות, korbanot, but what I understand is that
the פסול pasul comes here. I made it שלא לשמה. shelo lishma.
I wanted to bring שלמים shlamim and then I was like, oh
while I'm already here, let's make it a whatever פסח. pesach. I
forgot to bring פסח pesach or whatever, I decide to change what
the לשמה leshema קרבן, what is the intent of the קרבן? And
the פיגול is that I have a thought that's not relevant. I'm
like, oh, in three days I'll eat this in a different place
and then... But the effect is the same, it invalidates the... So
that's exactly the discussion, in what times the effect is the same
and in what times the effect is not the same. The effect
is the same again,
I'm a little bit scared here, but the effect is the same
in the זריקה because זריקה has to do with atonement, it's the
completion of the sacrifice. But maybe here in the קבלה kabbalah it
just happens, right, the blood just pours. I don't do anything. What
if I have a different thought at that time? Maybe that's okay.
And that's the discussion that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon bring, distinguishing the קבלה kabbalah from the others, or the
קבלה kabbalah? specifically from the זריקה,
a distinction we didn't have before, but turns out under a different
category. Notice, none of these commentators are כהנים. kohanim. You would expect
the כהנים kohanim to be the experts. Oh, you would have liked
somebody who was from the scene, report from the
scene. Interesting, hundreds of years after they stopped doing it anyway. Could
be, yeah.
I don't know if I mentioned it here but I think about
it like this. As this is the 70th anniversary, this is the
meaning of 70, did we talk about it here? 70 in our
history. For the rabbis of the משנה Mishnah גמרא, Gemara, we have
in our DNA 70 years between the first גלות galut and the
first coming back. So we might have thought oh, okay the temple
was destroyed but 70 years, 140 years, any time we're going
to be back now because that's what happened before. We don't have
in our DNA yet 1800 years of גלות, galut, like they don't
know where they're going forward, right, they just know what happened backwards.
So quick, quick על רגל אחת al regel achat
history, right. So 70 years after the destruction of the temple, around
70 years after the destruction of the temple was the בר כוכבא
Bar Kochba revolt,
failed. Let's wait another 70, 70 years after that רבי יהודה הנשיא
Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi writes the משנה, Mishnah, right, we're not yet there.
So like, when is this going to happen? Anytime now we need
to know exactly what we're going to do. And then it doesn't.
So it's like, it's not from experience but I think it's from
a sense of like also like, what are we going to do
without this whole system? We don't have a way to be מתקרב,
mitkarev, we don't have a way to come close, we don't have
a way to atone. Like, how are we going to make it
through
tomorrow let alone hundreds of years? Sure. When did the prayers become
the substitution? At what point did they say that this will be
your atonement? In that chronology, אנשי כנסת הגדולה Anshei Knesset HaGedolah is
before, right, is before zero, right, is before the destruction of the
temple. אנשי כנסת הגדולה, Anshei Knesset HaGedolah, the Men of the Great
Assembly, putting together עזרא Ezra and נחמיה Nechemiah putting together the תורה
Torah reading, major parts of the עמידה, Amidah, right, the ברכות. berachot.
But they still have the atonement, you're... Right. But they still overlap
and also as Rabbi Linds over yesterday said that even while the
temple was standing most people never actually brought קרבנות korbanot and so
תפילה tefillah was still going on at the time. Also if you
do hiking archaeology in Israel, the synagogues that date back to the
first second third century in the גליל Galil and the גולן, Golan,
these structures that we understand as synagogues. But my specific question was
in terms of the replacement for atonement, is there any thought about
the chronology?
When the prayers replaced the sacrifice in terms of... I can't give
you a date. I'm not sure.
You're suggesting we're still anticipating it because we need it for atonement
in this chronology you just gave. So at what point do you
think they realized we need another alternative, we need an alternative for
atonement? Really we never quite realized, you know, we always are sitting
on the edge with this like... but that the prayers should atone,
I'm asking you, follow... Yes, yeah, yeah, I can't give you a
date. But I think I've heard a different explanation. of why the
משנה Mishnah has so much of this קרבנות Korbanos stuff which is
that
by then the rabbis were already starting to realize that they needed
to do something going forward because if we sit here
without temple and without a substitute it's all going to disintegrate. Right.
And so in order to get buy-in from the people that their
new innovations have legitimacy they have to talk a lot about this
other stuff so it's like in the package maybe you don't notice
so much how much we're shifting. Right, right. Okay
I want to do just the other the second ראיה rayah because
we have two discussions on it and then we'll pause somewhere. So
let's okay
I want to try to be quick and also
touches on something he talks about on Tuesday. אמר רב מרי Amar
Rav Mari אף אנן נמי תנינא. Af anan nami tanina. Okay Rav
Mari brings a משנה Mishnah from מנחות. Menachot. זה הכלל Zeh haklal
כל הקומץ ונותן בכלי והמוליך והמקטיר. Kol hakometz venoten bikli vehamolich vehamaktir.
So he brings us the four עבודות avodot of the meal offering
or of the מנחה Minchah and parallels it to the four עבודות
here and we did this a little bit on Tuesday. We have
קומץ kometz נותן בכלי noten bikli
המוליך hamolich
והמקטיר. vehamaktir. Each one of those parallels another one of the עבודות
with the meat. קומץ Kometz is like שחיטה here so here we
say בשלמא bishlama קומץ היינו שוחט kometz haynu shochet מוליך היינו מוליך
molich haynu molich walking it walking it מקטיר נמי היינו זורק maktir
nami haynu zorek אלא נותן בכלי מאי ניהו? ella noten bikli mai
nihu? Okay so
קומץ kometz is like שוחט we prepare מוליך molich is like מוליך
molich we walk it מקטיר maktir is like the זריקה. What do
we do with the נותן בכלי? noten bikli? How do we know
that it's קבלה? kabbalah אילימא דדמי
לקבלה Ilima dedami lekabbalah מי דמי? mi dami? Oh
it's like קבלה kabbalah it's accepting
collecting the stuff right? We put it in a vessel and here
we collect it also in a vessel. So are they comparable? התם
ממילא הכא איהו קא שקיל ורמי. Hatam mimila hacha ihu ka shakil
verami. So in the blood it just gushes out to the kli
right? It happens ממילא mimila but in the מנחה Minchah you actually
have to collect it into the
vessel. אלא כיון דלא סגי דלא יהיב על כרחו עבודה חשובה היא.
Ella keivan delo sagi delo yahiv al korcho avodah chashuvah hi. But
we can't do it without it so therefore it's considered an עבודה
חשובה. avodah chashuvah. It's one of the four עבודות we can't do
without it. הכא נמי כיון דלא סגי דלא עביד לה על כרחו
הנו הולכה. Hacha nami keivan delo sagi delo avid lah al korcho
hanu holachah.
Here too
we're still in the חטאת chatat in regards to dipping the finger
in the blood of the inner חטאת. chatat. There's no exact equivalent
with the שלמים shelamim but it's not sufficient if the priest doesn't
if the כהן kohen doesn't perform it. It is therefore considered part
of the הולכה holachah part of conveying the blood
and it could have a פיגול status. But רגע rega לא לא
לא לעולם דדמי לקבלה. Lo lo lo leolam dedami lekabbalah. ודקאמרת
התם ממילא הכא איהו קא שקיל ויהיב. Vedeka'amart hatam mimila hacha ihu
ka shakil veyahiv.
I get it that you say that the קבלה happens ממילא mimila
that the blood just pours out by itself once you
slaughtered the animal better and here you have to actually place it
in the vessel. כיון דאידי ואידי מתן כלי הוא. Keivan deidi veidi
matan kli hu. But because both of them are a vessel then
I can learn from one to another. מה לי ממילא מה לי
קא שקיל ויהיב? Mah li mimila mah li ka shakil veyahiv? It
doesn't matter there's no difference to me if the blood spills by
itself or if the כהן kohen takes it and places it in
the vessel. By contrast the dipping one's finger in the blood of
the inner חטאת chatat has no equivalent. Like these we can compare
not perfect but they match pretty good. But the
dipping of the finger in the blood of the inner חטאת chatat
whether it has פיגול status has no equivalent in the שלמים shelamim
פסוק which we try to learn it from.
And therefore פיגול does not apply to it, and this is where
I would like to stop, and if someone else can pick up.
Thank you, Tamara. Thank you for being with us. So we still
have a